<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discouerie of the most secret and subtile practises of the Iesuites. Translated out of French</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04409)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 721:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discouerie of the most secret and subtile practises of the Iesuites. Translated out of French</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Eld] for Robert Boulton, and are to be sold at his shop in Smith-field, neere to Long-lane end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French translation not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ [-C4].</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The subtile practises of the Iesuites.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcouerie of the moſt ſecret and ſubtile practiſes <hi>of the</hi> IESVITES.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for <hi>Robert Boulton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Smith-field, neere to Long-lane end. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:2"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF the moſt ſecret deſſeings <hi>of the Ieſuits.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which <hi>Marcus Cato</hi> was wont to ſay, that it were a wonder if one Magician look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon an other ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to laugh; may well bee verified of the Ieſuites; that it were ſtrange if one Ieſuite conſidering an other, ſhould not laugh right out. I ſpeake not of ſimple Ieſuits, to whom eyther for the weakneſſe of their Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or for the good opinion they haue of their religion, or for the ſmall time they haue imployed in their company; their moſt ſecret ſubtilties are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. For they hold them vnder ſo ſeuere a diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, as not any one of them if hee haue not a very good ſent, can ſmell them out, and diſcouer the monſters hidden vnder the cloake of this rigour. I leaue theſe men to ſpeake of the Arch-Ieſuites them-ſelues, of the Regents, Fathers Prouincials and Generals of their Order, who haue ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in all ſort of wickedneſſe in generall, and particularly in Whordome, Treaſon, and Magicke Artes, as any man might rightly bee amazed, if a
<pb facs="tcp:8166:3"/>Ieſuite incountring his companion, and beholding himſelfe in him, as in a looking glaſſe, ſhould not laugh extreamly. I haue therefore reſolued to report ſome-things here, whereof I my ſelfe haue ſeene the greateſt part, the reſt I haue learned from Ieſuites themſelues, whom I could name, and doubtleſſe I will name them, if they doe but once open their mouths againſt that which I write. For this time I will briefly, and as it were in paſſing, trace them out, deferring to deſcribe them, which with the helpe of God I will more amply at another ſeaſon, ſetting downe their circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if thou entereſt into any colledge of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, eſpecially of thoſe which are built in any great &amp; well peopled towne: But why ſay I eſpecially, ſeeing there is not any one of them erected in any abiect or obſcure place? If I ſay, thou entreſt into any one of theſe colledges, obſerue at the firſt the Porter dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, the figure of a <hi>Charon</hi> or rather of a <hi>Cerberus.</hi> This man is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly of good yeares, if he be yong, they haue made very good triall of his fidelitie and ſilence. He vnderſtands the myſteries of their <hi>Cabale</hi> aſwell as any other. In his lodging you ſhall finde all ſorts of apparell, aſwell for men as women, of what condition ſoeuer. By this meanes the Ieſuites attired euery one like vnto the perſonage which they thinke they can beſt repreſent, practiſe ſtrange impoſtures. For ſome-times ſome of them attired like Soldiers, walke in publike places, and haunt Brothell houſes, abandoning them-ſelues to all diſſolution &amp; exceſſe. Some-times in the habite of Burgers, ſeeming to be <hi>Lutherans</hi> or <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> they obſerue in Innes, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-places, &amp; publike aſſemblies, what is ſaid of them,
<pb facs="tcp:8166:3"/>and the ſeuerall deſſeignes of euery man. Sometimes vnder the habit of Doctors, making ſhew to be good Catholikes, when as they know the lodgings of the richeſt among the people which haue children, they intrude themſelues, faining ſome other excuſe, and by ſundry practiſes purchaſe acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with them, This done, they exhort them to cauſe their children to be inſtructed in the Ieſuites colledge: for ſay they we haue ſtudied in their ſchoole, and God be thanked we haue not profited ill. Some-times vnder the habit of Gentlemen, hauing hired their furniture, they creepe into Princes Courts, &amp; pretend to be of their traine. Some-times alſo vnder the habite of poore paſſengers, they demand a <hi>Viaticum</hi> or reward, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Diuines &amp; Miniſters among the Proteſtants and Caluiniſts, to eſpie what they write againſt them. Theſe be the men my maiſters in my opinion, which haue ſo villanouſly affronted you vnto this day. But to the end that here-after yee may beware of ſuch ſpies, I will tell you what councels-they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and doe euen now take.</p>
            <p>Some demand of me whereto ſerue theſe habits for weomen? <hi>Terrence</hi> could neuer repreſent a Bawd ſo properly, to win the loue of yong ſtrumpets, as theſe Ieſuites do at this day, eſpecially this Porter of whom I ſpeake. For he by his flatteries and alurements diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers that eaſily, which his other companions, could not learne in the corners of their chapels &amp; temples, by means of their auriculer confeſſion. To effect this, he acquaints himſelfe with the pooreſt widowes, and ſillieſt women, as poore Spinſters, or Landreſſes, which ſend their daughters to receiue ſome Almes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:4"/>
            <p>When as this villaine hath by his inchantments drawne them to his humor, being before tattered, and torne, he attireth them in goodly apparell, which he hath in keeping, and hauing thus trimmed them vp, he brings them to my maiſters the Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by vnknowne wayes. And leaſt they ſhould be diſcoured, hee doth it not by day, but attends the twy-light. So they paſſe the night in feaſts and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, when as the yonger ſort amongſt them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue nothing. For to this end they haue vaults, yea they haue ſecret places vnder ground, in imitation of thoſe, which in old time did vowe them-ſelues to <hi>Venus,</hi> who gaue them-ſelues ſo brutiſhly to Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as <hi>Titus Liuius</hi> reports, that the <hi>Senate</hi> fearing the wrath of the Gods, did quite ruine this Stues, and Brothel-houſe. And thus much you may obſerue of the Ieſuites Porter. Where-vnto I will adde, that if happily any one ſeeming amazed, at this great aboundance of apparell, ſhall demand of them to what vſe it ſerues, they preſently anſwer him, that they keepe it to play Comedies. But this is not their chiefe end.</p>
            <p>If thou beeſt come to enter into their Temple, be aſſured that thou art vnder a heauen of Iron. For thou haſt ouer thy head a bloudy <hi>Mars,</hi> and not the God and Prince of Peace. Vnder thy feete thou haſt as it were a hideous Gulph of hell, and a ſhop of Tormentours. I will repreſent here faithfully what I my ſelfe haue ſeene.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Prague</hi> aboue the vault of their Temple, thou ſhalt finde thouſands of Chaines, and ſcourges of Iron, according to the vſe of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> On the one
<pb facs="tcp:8166:4"/>ſide are Canons placed, and a number of Muskets, and betwixt both many Lances, and Battle-axes. In the middeſt of the vault thou ſhalt ſee great heapes of Bullets. The like is ſeene in <hi>Cracouta</hi> in their temples; I doubt not but the like is to be found in other coledges. But wil you know where to all this ſerues. Truely I confeſſe that at the beginning I found it very ſtrange and prodigious. But behold their deſſeigne. The Ieſuites know wel that by reaſon of the troubles which they haue ſtirred vp, &amp; of their nottable villenies, they are in a manner generally hated of all the world, euen of the honeſteſt men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Papiſts. For they eſteeme not any one, no not them of their owne relligion, ſo as they may gratifie the Pope, were it with the ruine and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all the world, and the betraying of their owne countries. And therefore for that they are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall feares, by meanes of this warlike furniture they prouide in time for their ſafeties, for I haue heard them-ſelues ſay, they feare the like accident ſhould fall vpon them, as did vpon the Templers, who although they were good Catholikes, yet being grown inſuportable, by reaſon of their great Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Auarice, were by the conſent of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes, and the approbation of the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, all ſlaine and maſſacred almoſt in an inſtant throughout the world. They will haue their defence and armes placed in their Temples, to the end if any motiue happened, the Papiſts which ſhould run to their ſuckers, might be ſpeedely armed, or elſe if happely they of the contrary relligion ſhould come to ſpoyle them, they might bee beaten downe with
<pb facs="tcp:8166:5"/>armes, and ſtones which they would throw from aboue, I would gladly know if this bee not to make a denne of theeues of the houſe of prayer. But you ſhall heare things which you will admire and deteſt more: for all that hath beene ſaid are but Roſes and Flowers in regard of that which followeth.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Pauement of the Temple, in the Towne of <hi>Gratz</hi> in <hi>Stirria,</hi> and in other places, the haue Caues and priſons vnder ground, whereunto they deſcend by ſecret deuiſes. Thether they carry, (like to <hi>Cacus</hi> in <hi>Virgill</hi>) all their ſpoiles and treaſures, and lay vp great ſtore of Siluer. And thus not onely of their owne free will, but euen with an incredible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, theſe good men make profeſſion to be poore, ſupporting this pouerty with admirable patience, and curſing all ſuch as will not make profeſſion of pouerty as they doe, holdinge them vnworthy of ſo happy and ſweet a croſſe: they doe commonly place their treaſures, directly vnder the great Altar: by this meanes in ſinging Maſſe, they do ſacrifice to <hi>Mars</hi> aboue, and to Mammon vnderneath.</p>
            <p>There is alſo to bee ſeene in theſe priſons vnder ground, a Store-houſe full of coards, ſwords, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets, pincers, fetters, boults, and ladders, which ſerue to mannacle, torture, and miſerably to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thoſe which fal into the hands of ſuch as <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entius</hi> and <hi>Phalaris.</hi> They haue alſo ſtore of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fit for hangmen, hats, doublets and hoſe, the ſight or deſcription whereof would ſtrike terrour into any one. But alaſſe! to what end do theſe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men make ſuch preparation, who ſay they imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the perfect mildenes of our Sauiour? By theſe
<pb facs="tcp:8166:5"/>inſtruments they make captiue the vnderſtandings of their poore Shcollers, vnder their Ieſuiticall tirran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: for if they finde any one that they ſuſpect not to be conſtant in the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a good Ieſuite, or if they feare that eſcaping, he will diſcouer their ſecrets, they preſently clap both on his heeles, and after they haue made him to endure hunger and thirſt, they put him to death with moſt cruell torments. I inuent nothing I write the truth.</p>
            <p>There was a yong Gentleman of an excellent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, at <hi>Gratz</hi> in <hi>Stirria,</hi> called <hi>I mes Cluſſans</hi> of the Prouince of <hi>Karneten,</hi> who hauing beene very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably beaten with whippes, and ſtirrop-leathers, for a very light fault, threatninge them that hee would flye, and complaine publikely of their vniuſt procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt him, was by them put inot one of theſe priſons which wee haue deſcribed, from whence it is not ſaid that hee was euer releaſed: wee other yong Schollers which did ſtudy in the Colledge, did not doubt but that they put him to death by ſtrange tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>I will publiſh when time ſhall ſerue, this example of tiranny, the like whereof hath not beene heard, with all the circumſtances, in the place of this poore Gentleman, the which hee himſelfe had done if hee had liued: moreouer I will ſet forth to the viewe of all the world, another notable villany committed by the Ieſuites of <hi>Fulda,</hi> vpon the perſon of one named <hi>Martin,</hi> whoſe father and mother, are yet liuinge in the towne of <hi>Miltemberg,</hi> or <hi>Millberg</hi> in <hi>Franconia.</hi> And how many women thinke you that theſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue murthered, in theſe Caues? how many lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:8166:6"/>infants haue they ſlaine? How many young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of very rich-houſes haue they ſtolne away? For my part I hold it moſt certaine: how often haue wee poore nouices, heard the lamentations and ſhrikes of little Infants, their ſighes and cryes, which did ſo moue vs to pittie, as our haire ſtood right vp. The moſt ſimple thought they were the ſoules of the departed, and for my part I knew they were of thoſe that were newly borne, or that were newly ſlaine.</p>
            <p>Finally the Ieſuites to attayne vnto the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne degree of their deuiliſh mallice, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed in theſe places vnder-ground to make ſightes pleaſing vnto the Diuell, for they diſguiſe them-ſelues with maskes and fearefull Attires, and cauſing the nouices to come to ſee ſuch Tragedies, they preſent them-ſelues vnto them, caſting forth horrible cryes, to try their conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and reſolution, for they doe not admit to the Study of the Magike Art, ſuch as bee Tymerous and fearefull: But as incapable of great matters, they leaue them to the exerciſe of inferiour Arts, as for the moſt hardy, they obſerue them carefully, and reſerue them for the moſt Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtudies.</p>
            <p>But many times ſuch trialls ſucceede ill for them, as it happened at <hi>Prague</hi> in the yeare one thouſand ſixe hundred and two, in the month of September, For as the fiue cheefe Ieſuites, were buſied to terrifie their youth vnder the forme of Deuills, a ſixt, a very Deuill without
<pb facs="tcp:8166:6"/>doubt, came among them, and did ſo imbrace one of theſe fiue diſguiſed Diuells, as hee dyed within three dayes after. The Children talke openly of it in the Citty of <hi>Prague.</hi> Theſe Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites not-with-ſtanding without any amazement of ſo Tragicall an euent, comtinew ſtill obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately with Sacrilege, in the Study of Magike, In the knowledge whereof father <hi>Coton</hi> a French man excells all thoſe of his ſect. The French king did ſo much eſteeme him as hee did aſſiſt alwaies at his Table, and did commonly intertayne him: wee haue ſeene the queſtions which hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in the yeare one thouſand ſix hundred and fiue, to a young Mayden that was poſſeſt at Paris, whereby his wickedneſſe, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hee takes to ſpeake with the Diuell appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth playnly.</p>
            <p>The Ieſuits them-ſelues brag that hee hath a looking glaſſe of Aſtrology, wherein he made the King to ſee playnly what-ſoeuer his Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deſirded to know, and that there is nothing ſo ſecret, nor any thing propounded in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy councells of other Monarkes, which may not be ſeene or diſcouered by the meanes of this celeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall or rather diuiliſh glaſſe. It is by the ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of this coniuring Ieſuite that the reſt had promiſed vnto them-ſelues to draw vnto their party one of the greateſt Princes of the Empire, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were a Proteſtant, for they held him to be much giuen to the ſtudy of Magike. To ſuch of their
<pb facs="tcp:8166:7"/>nouices as they haue ſequeſtred to inſtruct in theſe Arts, they firſt expound vnto them the 900. propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſet vp at Rome by the Earle of <hi>Mirandola,</hi> Item <hi>Tritemius</hi> booke, with the Treatiſe of hidden Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie made by <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> Item <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> touching the conſtellation and ſignes of Planets, with the <hi>Steganographia</hi> of a certaine Abbot, and laſtly the Arte of <hi>Paul,</hi> for the concilliation of the reuelations. They ſay that <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> was very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this Arte, yea they make no doubt (the which is an inſupportable blaſpemy) the which I haue heard often from them-ſelues, and could name my authors, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> was a moſt perfect Magitian.</p>
            <p>Thus wee haue ſeene what concernes the Ieſuites Temple: wherevnto I will adde, that theſe holes and Caues vnder ground, whereof wee haue ſpoken, are moſt commonly vnder the Quier or the Galleries, &amp; not whereas the people are accuſtomed to kneele. Art thou come from their Temple to their Library? (for at this preſent I will not ſpeake any thing of their refectorie, where they eate, nor of their Chambers, nor Court dedicated for their recreation, nor of the nouriſhment of other Schollers which are vnder the Ieſuites charge, nor yet of the methode and order which they hold in their ſtudies, for I referre it to an other time, beſides that moſt of theſe things are very well knowne from others.</p>
            <p>Art thou come (I ſay) vnto their Liberies? looke on the right ſide, thou ſhalt finde it richely furniſhed with all ſorts of Authors. Their bookes are bound in Leather, or velome guilt or ſiluered. Thoſe whereof the vſe is ordinary, are chained to long deskes. As
<pb facs="tcp:8166:7"/>for their ſecret Library, it is onely lawfull for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to enter, and to make vſe of the bookes which they deſire.</p>
            <p>They yonger Ieſuites make vſe of the ordinary, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it lawfull for them without leaue from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, to extract any one word. Finally, in this Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there is not any hereticall bookes: but onely the moſt approoued bookes, &amp; all Catholikes. For as for Heretickes, they hold them vnworthy to haue any place among the reſt, for that it may bee they feare they ſhould infect and poiſon them. Wherefore looke vpon the left hand, thou ſhalt finde the bookes of theſe poore heretikes, all duſty and bound in ill fauoured skinnes and black parchment. Of theſe bookes euen the Fathers may not take any one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the permiſſion of the Regent, and the yonger ſort dare not demand them: before they haue by ſome Poem or other writing defamed with all ſorts of Iniuries the Author which they would ſee.</p>
            <p>In the middeſt of this Library, there is a ſtudie full of ſeates diuided one from another, the feeling bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Celeſtiall coulour. The Fathers ſet on the right ſide, and on the left they place the yonger, who notwithſtanding haue receiued ſome Orders among them.</p>
            <p>The other Nouices ſtand among the ordinary Pentioners, to the end they may obſerue them, and that diſcourſing with them they may make accompt of the mildneſſe and excellent order of the Ieſuites, eſpecially with the richeſt, and ſuch as bee ſole heires of ſome good houſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:8"/>
            <p>I will make no mention of their manner of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: But I will briefly deſcribe the Prouincialls examination, which I ſuppoſe hath not yet beene written.</p>
            <p>Euery Prouinciall receiues his name of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince or Realme which hee hath in charge to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee all that paſſeth. His duty is to viſite the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, to caſt vp the reuenewes thereof, and which is more, to obſerue carefully what great men doe breede vp their children in the Ieſuites Colledges, and how many there bee. Then hee muſt take an accompt how their Schollers doe multiply, and if their riches increaſe; who they bee that are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and how many they are: If hee finde not any, or if he perceiue that the Popiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion decayes in any ſort, and that their goods and reuenewes diminiſh, then hee reprocheth the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of Colledges of negligence and ſlouth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning them ſeuerely to recompence the fore-paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed loſſe. If he findes that they haue carryed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as they ought; that that they haue conuerted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; that they haue ſpared and gathered much toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then hee ſpares for no praiſes, extolling them vnto the third Heauen.</p>
            <p>More-ouer his charge is to enquire what Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Princes lye neareſt vnto them; if they doe liue vſually at home or abroad; to whome they are accuſtomed to goe; of what diſpoſition euery one is; wherein hee takes delight; if hee haue any care of the ſtate; if hee bee any way religious; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if hee bee giuen to drunkenneſſe, women, or
<pb facs="tcp:8166:8"/>Hunting; If hee haue any Catholikes in his Court, and what they bee; what the people ſay of their Prince, if hee fauour the aduerſaries; If the Paſtors of Churches bee learned and diligent men, or ſlouthfull and ignorant; If the profeſſion of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie doth flouriſh in the next Vniuerſitie; if the Diuines diſpute often, and againſt whom princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally; what Bookes, and of what ſubiect they haue lately ſet forth.</p>
            <p>If happily the Principall, and the Fathers anſwer pertinently to theſe queſtions, and to an infinite number of others, the Principall doth wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully commend their trauell and vigilancie: But if hee findes them not very curious of all theſe things, and that they anſwer not roundly, hee doth then blame them very ſharply.</p>
            <p>What doe you (ſaith hee) you ſlouthfull and idle men? Why doe you ſuffer the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to goe to ruine? What accompt ſhall wee giue vnto our Holy Father of his our negligence? Why doe you not meddle with affaires? what feare you? Why doe you not ſet your hands to the worke with an aſſured courage and reſolution? It is long ſince that yee ſhould haue done and ended that which I ſay: conſider the wonderfull vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Heritikes, and yet yee ſleepe for ſlouth. Hee blames them, and aminates them by theſe and ſuch like ſpeeches.</p>
            <p>Finally, hee enquires touching the Schollers, Penſioners, Nouices, and others, in what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber they are; how euery one doth profitte, to
<pb facs="tcp:8166:9"/>what ſtudy hee is inclined, if whether any one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them be no diſputer, but is ſcrupulous: for they will not ſet ſuch to the ſtudy of diuinity, before they be well practiſed in ſcholaſticall diſputations, and inſtructed in the Articles of their religion.</p>
            <p>The Prouincial moreouer hath charge to enquire if happily there bee any one among them, whoe if neceſſity required, would make no difficulty to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſome commendable Act, yea to looſe his life for the aduancement of the Church of Rome. This examination made and ſet downe in writing is ſent by the prouinciall to Rome, to their Generall, by whom it is immediately deliuered to the Pope.</p>
            <p>And thus nothing is done, or reſolued throughout all Chriſtendome, which comes not to the Popes knowledge by meanes of theſe Traytors of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. The Ieſuits alſo in a maner euery three yeeres, are tranſported by their Prouinciall, from one Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to another.</p>
            <p>For a concluſion I will adde the wonderfull ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Ieſuites, framed of late in theyr common Councell, the which they haue ſought, and doe at this day ſeeke to put in effect, for the ſubuerſion of the church &amp; the ſtate in the Romain Empire: their onely deſignes is how they ſhould diuide the Princes of the Empire one from another, and put the chiefe Doctors of the Church to death, to plant in theyr place the tiranny of Spaine, and the Popes Primacy in Germany. And hereof I remember I haue heard the Prouinciall <hi>Del-Rio</hi> diſcourſe, and theſe (as neere as I can remember) are theyr councels and practiſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt theyr aroiect is to ſee by what means, the
<pb facs="tcp:8166:9"/>mightieſt Princes of the Empire might be eſtranged one from another. The meanes to eſtrange them is, that there is diuerſity of religion amongſt them, and that the Emperour make a publike declaration, that liberty of Religion cannot bee allowed, before that reſtitution bee made of that which hath beene vſurped ſince the Treatie of <hi>Paſſaw:</hi> without doubt the Proteſtants will flatly refuſe this, let him leaue the Princes there, and demand the like of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall townes, who will either obey, or refuſe; if they obey, all goes well, if otherwiſe, let him proſcribe them, and abandon them in prey to the neighbour Princes, and alwayes a <hi>Lutheran</hi> to one, and a <hi>Calue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist</hi> to an other: for the Papiſts did not thinke that the Proteſtant Princes would haue beene ſo diſcreet in the buſineſſe of <hi>Donawerd,</hi> but that the <hi>Prince Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Wertemberg</hi> at the leaſt would haue oppoſed them-ſelues againſt the Duke of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaria,</hi> the which if they had done, they them-ſelues had beene ſubiect to proſcription, and all meanes of pacification, not onely with the Papiſts, but alſo with the <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> taken away: But for that they haue carried them-ſelues with more conſideration then was expected, the Ieſuites haue had recourſe to theſe ſubtilties: for one or two Imperiall Townes being proſcribed, there is not any Prince that will bee ſo ſtayed, but had rather that in the common Prey, they ſhould reſpect him before any other that ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it. And thus much for the Generall.</p>
            <p>Touching that which concernes particulars, the Ieſuites deſſeigne is to labour to deuide the Princes
<pb facs="tcp:8166:10"/>of Saxonie, to the end that their power might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. They haue found meanes to effect it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly. Firſt troubling the affaires in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Archbiſhopricke of Magdebourg, whereas the Elector of <hi>Cologne</hi> is already receiued for Prior.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if this doe not ſucceed according to their intentions, they muſt pretend ſome reaſon which ſhall make the Elector of Saxony to be held vnworthy of the Electorſhip. For if in old time the Princes of the Empire did reiect <hi>Wenceſtaus</hi> from the Imperiall Maieſtie, for that they found him baſe and effeminate. Why may not the Emperour by as iuſt a reaſon depriue the Elector of Saxonie from the Electorall dignity, being euery day drunke? Let him giue and reſtore this dignity to the familie of <hi>Weinmar,</hi> and for that theſe Princes are yet very young, let him make <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and vigilant Prince, Adminiſtrator of the Electorſhip.</p>
            <p>VVithout doubt this would cauſe great troubles throughout all the countrie of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and by this meanes they ſhould ruine them-ſelues with their owne forces, and make them-ſelues vnable to reſiſt their common enemy if hee comes vpon them. As for that which concernes them of <hi>Brandebourg,</hi> and <hi>Pomerania,</hi> they muſt labour ſo to reconcile the King of <hi>Polland</hi> (allyed to the Emperour) with his Vncle the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as they may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide <hi>Pruſſia.</hi> Where-vnto without doubt the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of <hi>Brandebourg</hi> will oppoſe with all his force.
<pb facs="tcp:8166:10"/>As for the <hi>Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> he muſt bee forced to diuide the inheritance equall with the <hi>Landgraue Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis</hi> his couſen, and to reſigne the adminiſtration of <hi>Herffild</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Writzburg:</hi> If not, let him be proſcribed, and his country aſſigned to the ſaid <hi>Landgraue.</hi> Finally it is eaſie to ſet diuiſion betwixt the Duke of Wirtemberg and the Electour Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, if they preſſe the Duke to reſtore certaine Abaies, and for want thereof that hee bee proſcribed, and that certaine neare Moneſtaries, may be aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the Elector, among others one (which they ſay) he hath long demanded. Behold the fatal deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeines of the Ieſuites, which I my ſelfe haue heard from their owne mouthes, not without great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and amazement. They haue alſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the which at this preſent I doe not wel remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. To this end alſo tends the peace of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> and that of <hi>Hungarie:</hi> But I beleeue that GOD hath ſo gouerned all, for the good and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcruation of his Church, as they are forced to ſee the Hatreds, which they indeuored to ſowe amonge the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> to be kindled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Emperour and his Brother <hi>Mathias,</hi> moſt deare and obedient children to our Holy Father. Moreouer the Ieſuites new deſigne is, to ſend throughout Chriſtendome, certaine mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers and poyſoners, to poyſon the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Doctors of the Churches aſwell <hi>Lutherans</hi> as <hi>Caluiniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They hold that they ſhall bee ſo cunning in this Art, as the very diſhes, Baſons, kettles,
<pb facs="tcp:8166:11"/>and other ordinary implements of houſehold, hauing beene once infected with their poyſon, ſhal not looſe the force although they be tenne-times clenſed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I would intreat all good and true Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the Church, to bee wary hereafter how they truſt any one that hath not beene well knowne vnto them. Theſe things had neuer come into my thought or imagination, if my ſelfe had not heard them with many others, from the cheefe companions of that Sect.</p>
            <p>I thought it my duty to ſet them forth for the good of the Church and of my Country, tracing them onely at this preſent, with hope (if it pleaſe God) to deſcribe them when time ſhall ſerue, and to paint them out in ther liuely coullers, with all the circumſtances both of places and perſons.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8166:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
